Ren d'Harnoncourt Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series IV: Directors Correspondence, 1949-1968
  - Steering Committee of the 30th Anniversary Drive, 1959; Minutes and notes of preliminary meetings. (Folder IV.111)
  - Steering Committee of the 30th Anniversary Drive, 1960; Minutes of Meetings. (Folder IV.112)
  - Staff Committee of the 30th Anniversary Drive, 1959-60; Minutes of Meetings. (Folder IV.113)
  - Architecture and Design, 1965-67; Correspondence. (Folder IV.114)
  - Architecture and Design, 1959-64; Correspondence. (Folder IV.115)
  - Architecture and Design, 1955-58; Correspondence. (Folder IV.116)
  - Architecture and Design, 1950-51; Correspondence. (Folder IV.117)
  - Architecture and Design, 1949-51; Correspondence. (Folder IV.118)
  - Business Managers Office, 1959-60; Correspondence. (Folder IV.119)
  - Business Managers Office, 1957; Correspondence about the securing and renewal of municipal licenses and permits. (Folder IV.120)
  - Business Managers Office, 1954-55; Correspondence and financial reports. (Folder IV.121)
  - Business Managers Office, 1950-53; Correspondence and financial reports. (Folder IV.122)
  - Business Managers Office, 1947-48; Interoffice memos, committee and financial reports. Draft report to the Board of Trustees of MoMA by the Committee on Policy (12/17/47). (Folder IV.123)
  - Circulating Exhibitions, 1965-68; Correspondence of Waldo Rasmussen and others in connection with national and international circulating exhibitions. Includes correspondence about Two Decades of American Painting, scheduled for showing in Japan in late 1966 and early 1967. List of works included in that exhibition. Lists of proposed circulating exhibitions for the 1965-66, 1966-67, and 1968-69 seasons. (Folder IV.124)
  - Circulating Exhibitions - Ben Heller Collection, 1960-65; Correspondence about the exhibition of the Ben Heller Collection and the problems following it. Correspondents include Ben Heller, Porter McCray, Waldo Rasmussen, RDH, Richard Koch, and Daniel Goldreyer of Daniel Goldreyer, Ltd., Conservation of Paintings. (Folder IV.125)
  - Circulating Exhibitions, 1959-64; Correspondence of Porter McCray, Waldo Rasmussen, and of others in connection with national and international circulating exhibitions. Printed catalog of Circulating Exhibitions for 1963-64. (Folder IV.126)
  - Circulating Exhibitions, 1956-58; Correspondence of Porter McCray and others in connection with national circulating exhibitions. 1 TLS (copy) Philip Goodwin - Porter McCray (4/15/57) about problems with M0MAs domestic circulating exhibitions, and the growing importance of the international program. (Folder IV.127)
  - Circulating Exhibitions, 1954-55; Correspondence of Porter McCray and others in connection with circulating exhibitions. (Folder IV.128)
  - Collections - Conservation, 1965-67; Correspondence of Jean Volkmer, Conservator, and others about the Conservation Department. Report by Caroline Keck, Consultant Conservator, on plans for An Expanded Conservation Department (3/15/65). (Folder IV.129)
  - Collections - Conservation, 1957-63; Correspondence of Jean Volkmer, Conservator, and others about the Conservation Department. Several memos, among them one from AHB to RDH (10/28/58), discussing problems in the establishment of a new conservation laboratory, which had become essential following the fire of 1958 in which several pictures were damaged. (Folder IV.130)
  - Education Department - Institute of Modern Art, 1960-64; Correspondence between RDH and Victor DAmico, Director of the Institute. Minutes of 5th Annual Meeting of the Corporation of the Institute of Modern Art, 11/19/64. Brochure and press release about art classes and workshops held on Long Island during the summer. (Folder IV.131)
  - Education Department - Institute of Modern Art, 1965-67; Correspondence between RDH and Victor DAmico, Director of the Institute. Minutes of 6th Annual Meeting of the Corporation of the Institute of Modern Art (1/26/1967), at which a letter from Blanchette Rockefeller regretfully tendering her resignation from the Board of Trustees and Corporation of the Institute was read. Minutes of Meetings of the Board of Trustees, 6/17/65, 12/14/65, 6/16/66, 1/26/67, 5/31/67, 10/26/67. (Folder IV.132)
  - Education Department - Institute of Modern Art, 1961-64; Correspondence between RDH and Abdul Imao, a young artist from the Philippines who received a travel grant from the Institute. 1 TLS Blanchette Rockefeller - RDH (5/17/63) enclosing a check for $400 for the travel grant for Abdul Imao. Newspaper clipping with photograph of Abdul Imao. (Folder IV.133)
  - Education Department - Institute of Modern Art, 1960-62; Correspondence, financial and other reports, about the Childrens Art Carnival held in India in 1962. Copy of letter from RDH - Mrs. John F. Kennedy (5/31/62) thanking her for sending the photograph taken at the Reception for Andre Malraux. RDH correspondence with Miss Letitia Baldrige, Social Secretary at the White House, about the Andre Malraux dinner and thanking her for her help with the Indian project, particularly the television and press coverage of Mrs. Kennedys transmittal of the Carnival to Mrs. Gandhi. Correspondence with The Asia Society which contributed money to the Childrens Carnival. (Folder IV.134)
  - Education Department, 1959-60; Correspondence and reports about a proposed Childrens Exhibition to be staged by MoMA in the White House in 1960. (Folder IV.135)
  - Education Department, 1955-58; Correspondence and reports on the work of the department and proposals for reorganizing it - discussion about the Committee on Art Education. Copy of Coming Events Cast Their Shadows: A Reappraisal of Art Education, a lecture given by Victor DAmico as Chairman of the National Committee on Art Education at its 16th Annual Conference held at MoMA, 4/26/58. (Folder IV.136)
  - Education Department, 1954-56; Correspondence about a proposed European summer seminar, and about a proposed summer painting class to be given by Victor DAmico on Long Island. Brochure on the 12th Annual Conference sponsored by the Committee on Art Education, art education and the creative process, 3/18 - 3/21/54. (Folder IV.137)
  - Education Department, 1952; Material on art education and television. Young Peoples Gallery. Speech before the Committee on Art Education by NAR (5/22/52). Press release about Through The Enchanted Gate, a series on art education for children presented by WNBT in cooperation with MoMA (5/5/52). New York Herald Tribune clipping on Through The Enchanted Gate (5/25/52). Photographs of design for a proposed childrens playground for the UN designed by Isamu Noguchi and Julian Whittlesey, shown at the MoMA Young Peoples Gallery 3/24-4/27/1952. (Folder IV.138)
  - Education Department, 1950-51; Departmental correspondence. 1 TLS George Grosz - RDH (5/22/1950). (Folder IV.139)
  - Education Department, 1950-51; Departmental correspondence. (Folder IV.140)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1965-68; Departmental correspondence. Correspondence of Monroe Wheeler, Director of Exhibitions and Publications. (Folder IV.141)
  - Publications, 1967; Departmental correspondence. Correspondence of Gray Williams, Jr. who became Director of Publications in late 1966. (Folder IV.142)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1959-64; Departmental correspondence. (Folder IV.143)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1955-58; Departmental correspondence. (Folder IV.144)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1952; Correspondence between MW, AHB, James Johnson Sweeney, and Michel Seuphor about publication of a book on Mondrian. (Folder IV.145)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1951; Correspondence about current exhibitions and plans for future exhibitions. Tentative exhibition schedules. Correspondents include RDH, AHB, MW, and Andrew Ritchie of MoMA, and Daniel Catton Rich, Director of the Art Institute of Chicago. Much of the correspondence is about the Matisse exhibition which opened in November 1951. (Folder IV.146)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1951; Tentative exhibition schedules for 1951-54. Proposed Exhibitions Budget 1951-52. Architecture and Design exhibition schedule for 1951-52. (Folder IV.147)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1950-51; Correspondence about current and future exhibitions, and current and future publications. (Folder IV.148)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1950-51; RDH correspondence with other museum directors and friends about exhibitions at other institutions. (Folder IV.149)
  - Exhibitions and Publications, 1945-51; Correspondence about prospective exhibitions to be held in other countries. Copy of list of exhibitions and other materials supplied by MoMA to countries outside the U.S. 1945-50. Copy of list prepared by Porter McCray of requests for exhibition material outside the U.S. 1940-48. (Folder IV.150)
  - Publications, 1964-65; Correspondence of M.J. Gladstone, Associate Director of Publications. (Folder IV.151)
  - Publications, 1964; Applications and correspondence about candidates for position in the Publications Department. (Folder IV.152)
  - Publications Committee, 1963; Minutes of Publications Committee Meeting, April 16, 1963. (Folder IV.153)
  - Publications, 1959; Drafts of proposed MoMA Journal and Pamphlet. (Folder IV.154)
  - Publications Committee, 1959; Memos, Minutes of Publications Committee Meetings, proposals and listings for a 5-year Publications Program. (Folder IV.155)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Architecture U.S.A., 1965; Correspondence about the exhibition,Architecture U.S.A., and about the booklet by the same title by Arthur Drexler. (Folder IV.156)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Architecture Without Architects, 1964-66; Correspondence with Bernard Rudofsky about the exhibition,Architecture Without Architects, and about the book related to it, and inter-office memos. (Folder IV.157)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:The Racing Car: Toward a Rational Automobile, 1965-66; Correspondence and notes from a discussion about the exhibition. (Folder IV.158)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Structures for Sound - Musical Instruments by Francois & Bernard Baschet, 1965-66; Correspondence. (Folder IV.159)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Three Structures by Buckminster Fuller, 1959; Correspondence. (Folder IV.160)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Buildings for Business and Government, 1956-57; Correspondence. (Folder IV.161)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Design for Sport, 1962; Correspondence. (Folder IV.162)
  - Architecture and Design -International Competition for Low Cost Furniture Design, 1947-50; Correspondence. Invitation to inaugural dinner for the Competition, program for the dinner, and invitation to a cocktail party at which NAR will present the awards to the winners of the Competition. (Folder IV.163)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Textiles and Ornamental Arts in India, 1954-55; Correspondence: MW, Edgar Kaufmann, Jr., Porter McCray and RDH with people in India who had cooperated with MoMA in making the exhibition possible; also interoffice memos. Press release 10/1/54. (Folder IV.164)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Japanese Exhibition House, 1957; Correspondence with The Asia Foundation which made a contribution to MoMA for expenses incurred by the move of the Japanese House to the Fairmount Park in Philadelphia. (Folder IV.165)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Japanese Exhibition House, 1953-56; Correspondence about the Japanese House, designed by Junzo Yoshimura, and exhibited in the garden of MoMA in the summers of 1954 and 1955. Survey of visitors at Japanese House, January 1956. Press release about move to Philadelphia, June 1956. RDH correspondence with Sadao Iguchi, Ambassador of Japan, about possibility of moving the Japanese House to Washington, Oct.-Dec. 1955. (Folder IV.166)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Japanese Exhibition House, 1955-58; Correspondence about financial matters relating to Japanese House. (Folder IV.167)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Japanese Exhibition House, 1954; Correspondence about financial matters relating to Japanese House. (Folder IV.168)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Louis I. Kahn, 1966; Correspondence about the finances of the exhibition and dinner preceding it. Press release describing the exhibition and Mr. Kahns career (4/26/1966). Statement by Professor Vincent Scully on the Architecture of Louis I. Kahn. (Folder IV.169)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:New Lamps, 1949-50; Correspondence about the exhibition - also some correspondence about a lamp competition and a competition for low-priced furniture. (Folder IV.170)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Latin American Architecture since 1945, 1955; One letter to Arthur Drexler from Emilio Duhart H., Architect, Santiago, Chile, in response to invitation to the dinner and special private preview of the exhibition. (Folder IV.171)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Le Corbusier: Buildings in Europe and India, 1955-57, 1962-63; Correspondence and material on an exhibition about Le Corbusier's work which eventually took place in 1963. (Folder IV.172)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:The New City: Architecture and Urban Renewal, 1965-67; Correspondence. Program for the luncheon given for the opening of the exhibition, which was co-sponsored by the City of New York. Mayor John V. Lindsay opened the exhibition and presided at the luncheon. List of Trustees and Special Guests who attended a cocktail party and special viewing of the exhibition. 1 TLS John V. Lindsay - RDH (7/8/66) expressing his interest in the exhibition, and suggesting that it be co-sponsored by New York City. 1 TLS Robert F. Kennedy - RDH (1/14/67) thanking him for invitation to luncheon, and regretting that his schedule will not permit him to accept. (Folder IV.173)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:The Package, 1958-59; Correspondence. (Folder IV.174)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Travel Posters, 1956-57; Correspondence. (Folder IV.175)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Textiles USA, 1956; Correspondence, some of it with American Fabrics magazine, which co-sponsored the exhibition, press releases, and copy of the data sheet used by prospective participants in the exhibition. (Folder IV.176)
  - Architecture and Design Exhibitions:Frank Lloyd Wright Drawings, 1959-62; Correspondence. RDHs remarks at dinner for Mrs. Wright given before the opening of the exhibition on March 12, 1962, and list of people at the dinner. (Folder IV.177)
  - Exhibitions:Americans 1963, Memos re: exhibition expenses. (Folder IV.178)
  - Exhibitions:The Art of Assemblage, 1961; One letter about dates when the show will be in other U.S. cities, and inter-office memos. (Folder IV.179)
  - Exhibitions:Art Nouveau, 1959-60; Correspondence, much of it with other museums in U.S. and in other countries. (Folder IV.180)
  - Exhibitions:Max Beckmann, 1962-66; Correspondence, much of it with other museums in U.S. and in other countries. (Folder IV.181)
  - Exhibitions:Bonnard and His Environment, Correspondence. Press release (10/7/64) contains information on the exhibition and on Bonnards life and the reasons for his estate being tied up in litigation in France from his death in 1947 until 1963. (Folder IV.182)
  - Exhibitions:Jean Dubuffet, 1961-62; Correspondence. 1 TLS (copy) Jean Dubuffet - Peter Selz (3/3/62) thanking him for organizing the magnificent exhibition of his work at MoMA, and for the receptions at his apartment and the Museum Guest House. (Folder IV.183)
  - Exhibitions:Max Ernst, 1959-61; Correspondence. 1 TLS (copy) Max Ernst - MW (9/9/60) asking about how arrangements for the exhibition were progressing. Letters from MW to Max Ernst, and to Roland Penrose, who was writing a book on Ernst. (Folder IV.184)
  - Exhibitions:French Masterworks, 1954-55; Correspondence with French museum officials about this exhibition - one of several celebrating MoMAs 25th anniversary - which contained 15 paintings by French masters of the 19th century, 13 from the Louvre and one each from the museums of Albi and Lyon. (Folder IV.185)
  - Exhibitions:French Masterworks, 1954-55; Correspondence. (Folder IV.186)
  - Exhibitions:French Masterworks, 1954-55; Correspondence. (Folder IV.187)
  - Exhibitions:Futurism, 1960-61; Correspondence. (Folder IV.188)
  - Exhibitions:German Art of the 20th Century, 1957-58; Correspondence about bringing from Europe three German scholars responsible for assembling the exhibition and producing its catalogue. (Folder IV.189)
  - Exhibitions:German Art of the 20th Century, 1957; Correspondence about the German Film Festival held in connection with the exhibition. (Folder IV.190)
  - Exhibitions:German Art of the 20th Century, 1957; Correspondence about the German music evening held on October 14, 1957 in connection with the exhibition. 1 ALS John Cage - RDH (10/10/57) accepting invitation to the concert. 1 TLS Aaron Copland - RDH (10/1/57) regretting that he will be unable to come. 1 TLS Philip Johnson - RDH (10/2/57) accepting invitation. (Folder IV.191)
  - Exhibitions:Giacometti, 1964-65; Correspondence. 1 ALS Alberto Giacometti - RDH (5/19/64) (In French). 1 TLS Theodore Roszak - RDH (10/16/65). (Folder IV.192)
  - Exhibitions:Arshile Gorky 1904-1948, 1962-64; Correspondence and press release about the exhibition. (Folder IV.193)
  - Exhibitions:Gunter Haese, 1964-65; Correspondence. (Folder IV.194)
  - Exhibitions:The Sidney and Harriet Janis Collection, 1967-68; Correspondence. (Folder IV.195)
  - Exhibitions:Ren Magritte, 1965; Correspondence. (Folder IV.196)
  - Exhibitions:Henri Matisse, 1964-66; Correspondence. (Folder IV.197)
  - Exhibitions:Robert Motherwell, 1965-66; Correspondence. (Folder IV.198)
  - Exhibitions:Reuben Nakian, 1965-66; Correspondence. 2 ALS Reuben Nakian - RDH (12/13/65, 12/21/65). 1 ALS Reuben Nakian - Mrs. Bliss Parkinson (6/26/66). (Folder IV.199)
  - Exhibitions:New Images of Man, 1959; Correspondence. (Folder IV.200)
  - Exhibitions:The New Japanese Painting and Sculpture, 1964-67; Correspondence. (Folder IV.201)
  - Exhibitions:Emil Nolde: 1867-1956, 1960-63; Correspondence. (Folder IV.202)
  - Exhibitions:Eduardo Paolozzi, 1964; Correspondence. (Folder IV.203)
  - Exhibitions:15 Polish Painters, 1959-61; Correspondence. (Folder IV.204)
  - Exhibitions:Redon-Moreau-Bresdin, 1961; 1 memo, MW - RDH (8/21/61) re: Loans from the Louvre. (Folder IV.205)
  - Exhibitions:The Responsive Eye, 1964-65; Correspondence. (Folder IV.206)
  - Exhibitions:Medardo Rosso: 1858-1928, 1963; Correspondence. (Folder IV.207)
  - Exhibitions:The Taste of a Connoisseur: Paul J. Sachs Collection, 1965-67; Correspondence. (Folder IV.208)
  - Exhibitions:Sculpture in Glass, 1964-65; Correspondence. (Folder IV.209)
  - Exhibitions:New Spanish Painting and Sculpture, 1958-60; Correspondence. (Folder IV.210)
  - Exhibitions:New Spanish Painting and Sculpture, 1958; Photographs and brochure. (Folder IV.211)
  - Exhibitions:Mark Tobey, 1962; Correspondence. (Folder IV.212)
  - Exhibitions:Toulouse-Lautrec, 1956; Correspondence about the exhibition, most of it about the Museums Toulouse-Lautrec posters which were put in many places in New York City and the surrounding area. (Folder IV.213)
  - Exhibitions:Turner: Imagination and Reality, 1960-66; Correspondence. (Folder IV.214)
  - Exhibitions:The Artist in his Studio - Photographs by Alexander Liberman, 1959-60; Correspondence. (Folder IV.215)
  - Exhibitions:The Bitter Years: 1935-41, 1962-63; Correspondence. (Folder IV.216)
  - Exhibitions:The Family of Man, 1955-68; Correspondence. (Folder IV.217)
  - Exhibitions:The Family of Man, 1955-68; Correspondence. Copy of the exhibition catalog. (Folder IV.218)
  - Exhibitions:Dorothea Lange, 1965-66; Correspondence. 1 TLS Stewart L. Udall, Secretary of the Interior - RDH (1/10/66). 1 TLS Supreme Court Justice Abe Fortas - RDH (12/22/65). Both letters were sending regrets at not being able to attend the shows opening dinner. (Folder IV.219)
  - Exhibitions:Once Invisible, 1966-67; Correspondence. (Folder IV.220)
  - Exhibitions:Television U.S.A.: Thirteen Seasons, 1961-64; Correspondence, much of it with people at CBS, NBC, and ABC. Brochure with details of the 54 TV programs selected from 1948 to 1961 which were shown in the Museum Film Auditorium, Feb. 5 through May 2, 1963, under the supervision of the Museums Film Library. (Folder IV.221)
  - Exhibitions:U.P.A (United Productions of America) Form in the Animated Cartoon, 1955; Correspondence. (Folder IV.222)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: Sam Francis, 1964-65; Correspondence. Copy of TLS Sam Francis - Peter Selz (3/5/65) canceling the show. (Folder IV.223)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: The Heroic Years, 1960-61; Brief correspondence between JTS, MW, AHB, and RDH. (Folder IV.224)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: Landscape, 1946; 1950; Correspondence, copies of articles on landscape gardening. (Folder IV.225)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: Malevich, 1961-67; Correspondence. (Folder IV.226)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: Manet, 1962-65; Correspondence. (Folder IV.227)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: Marlborough Gallery, 1963-64; Correspondence (Folder IV.228)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: Barnett Newman, Stations of the Cross, 1967; Correspondence. Note: The Stations of the Cross were shown in a later exhibition at MoMA -Barnett Newman, 10/21/71 - 1/10/72. (Folder IV.229)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: Signs on Broadway, 1955; Correspondence and tentative budget. (Folder IV.230)
  - Proposed Exhibitions: Noguchi, 1966-67 (Folder IV.231)
  - Film Department, 1967-68; Departmental correspondence. (Folder IV.232)
  - Film Library: Czech Film Project, 1966; Correspondence. (Folder IV.233)
  - Film Library, 1965-66; Departmental Correspondence. Letters of congratulation to RDH, and to Willard Van Dyke on Mr. Van Dykes appointment as Director of the Film Library in November 1965. (Folder IV.234)
  - Film Library: New York Film Festival, 1963-64; Correspondence about the first New York Film Festival, which was presented by MoMA, Lincoln Center, and the British Film Institute. Program of the Film Festival, which was held September 10-19, 1963. (Folder IV.235)
  - Film Library: Film on the Museum, 1960; Memos about a proposed film on the Museum. (Folder IV.236)
  - Film Library: Dietrich Benefit, 1959; Correspondence and press release about An Evening with Marlene Dietrich, a gala benefit for the MoMA Film Library on April 7, 1959, preceding the start on April 8 of Marlene Dietrich: Image and Legend - a 12 week program of full-length Dietrich films. (Folder IV.237)
  - Film Library: Eastman House Vaults, 1958-59; Correspondence. (Folder IV.238)
  - Film Library: Kirk Bond, 1957-58; Correspondence. (Folder IV.239)
  - Film Library, 1955-58; Departmental correspondence. 1 TLS Paul Rotha - RDH (11/3/1958) thanking him and his colleagues for putting on the season of my work and for the very enjoyable party you gave me. (Folder IV.240)
  - Film Library: 3rd International Art Film Festival in America, 1956-57; Correspondence and press release. (Folder IV.241)
  - Film Library: French Film Cycle, 1956-58; Correspondence. (Folder IV.242)
  - Film Library: Exchange of Films with Rio de Janeiro, 1957-58; Correspondence. (Folder IV.243)
  - Film Library: Film Preservation, 1955-57; Correspondence and press release. (Folder IV.244)
  - Film Library: Puerto Rican Film Evenings, 1957; Correspondence. (Folder IV.245)
  - Film Library: Film Withdrawal, 1956-57; Correspondence and schedule of operation costs, 1935-55. Correspondence about damage caused to the Film Librarys circulation program by several of the major motion picture companies requiring that MoMA withdraw from circulation its 16mm prints of many historic films. (Folder IV.246)